hi I'm Tony nor and this is a free 1hour
tutorial for the Canon 5D Mark I if you
have a different camera you can go to
this URL sdp.io tutorials and we have
tutorials for just about every camera
out there you can share that with your
friends first I'm not going to cover
every little menu item and nitpicky
thing in the camera I'm just going to
cover those things that I think are
valuable to photographers I'm also not
going to go over super Elementary
aspects of Photography because I'm going
to assume if you're using this Pro body
that you at least have some experience
with photography but I will keep in mind
that you might be switching over from
Sony or Nikon or some other system so
I'll explain some of the basics if I
bore you look at the description down
below you can jump ahead to different
parts of the video if you already know
everything about the camera I do have
lens recommendations at the end of the
video so you might skip forward to those
things let's get started uh I want to
talk a little bit about the battery it
uses the lp e6n battery which which is
basically the same battery since the
Canon 5D Mark II so you can continue to
use your old batteries if you're
upgrading I just want to mention go
ahead and get at least one more of these
I I found that a single battery can last
you a couple of days of normal travel
shooting or you can probably get through
a typical wedding with a single battery
uh however if you're shooting video it's
going to run out faster and you don't
ever really want to be stranded you have
to use the battery charger you can't USB
charge charge these things and beware of
generic non-canon batteries because they
will work but I find that they work
great for some number of weeks two three
weeks maybe six weeks and then they
start to die really quickly so as a
result I simply don't use them anymore
let's move on to the memory cards this
camera if you pull this slot back it has
two memory cards One SD card one CF
card the CF card is probably going to be
your primary card because the if
interface tends to be a little bit
faster however I strongly encourage you
to populate both slots with cards of
equal size and the bigger the better and
then configure the camera to write to
both cards simultaneously because while
not everybody has had a memory card
failure maybe most people haven't they
do fail I've had three I think three or
four fail over the course of my career
so it happens and if you're in the
middle of a wedding and your card fails
you might end up with a very pissed off
family and you might end up losing a
client and actually might impact your
career once the reviews come in if you
care about your pictures use two memory
card slots and configure it to write to
both I'll show you how to do that
quickly Once you turn the camera on with
this switch there hit the menu button
and then right it's the very first thing
here uh under oops I forgot I go tap in
the screen so go to the wrench icon up
here and then on page one go to record
function and card folder selection and
for record function set that to record
to multiple and you can see now it's
recording to both memory cards
simultaneously you'll notice if it plays
back it's playing back from the CF card
by default uh if you record video it
will not record to both cards
simultaneously it'll just record to
probably your CF card one more point
about the memory cards if you're
recording 4K video the codec that this
camera uses is exceptionally inefficient
as a result 128 gig card like those that
I tend to use only stores about 30
minutes a video so buy bigger cards than
you think you might need like a 256 card
would just get you an hour of video it's
definitely not too much let's go over
the physical ports on the camera I'm
assuming you can figure out the memory
card and Battery slots okay over here on
the side you can see up here at the top
you have a PC sync cord hopefully you're
not using this anymore it's a hold over
from the early 1910s and 20s I think
that was common and it's terribly
unreliable and since fall out but you
can still trigger just about any flash
with it pull this over open and you can
see your video connectors the mic jack
up here and the headphone jack down here
if you're recording audio you'll want to
be using both of those and if you're not
then you're probably doing something
wrong the other little rubbered sleeve
here is covering up your HDMI port and
your usb3 Port this is a mini HDMI port
here you could use it to go out to a
field recorder when you record video
however it only outputs 1080p through
the the mini HDMI port it does not
output 4K video so you could use it to
monitor something or to record a lower
quality feed through a field monitor but
you can't look at your 4K video that way
the other Port here is the usb3 port
that's exceptionally useful for
tethering in our studio we have a
separate video about this but we connect
by USB 3 into a computer running capture
one and that makes the workflow go much
much faster if you had a previous Canon
you'll be surprised by this but the
remote connector for like a remote sync
uh a remote trigger shutter trigger is
here on the front now it's just used to
be on the side now it's on the front
otherwise you can still use your same
remote triggers if you had a 5D Mark II
or an earlier
camera once you take a picture uh I just
want to show you quickly I'm just going
to take a picture here it'll pop up on
the screen automatically you can review
it by pressing the play button there hit
the info button over here in the upper
left corner to cycle through different
bits of information about it so you can
see if I press it once it shows me the
shutter speed the aperture the iso as
well as you know the format of a large
JPEG and if I push it again it'll
actually show me the histogram which
tells me how bright or dark the picture
is if you don't know what a histogram is
I have a book stuning digital
photography chapter 4 will tell you what
the histogram is um that's about what
there is to know about uh reviewing
pictures one thing I really like about
these Canon cameras is this rate button
so if I love that picture let's you know
what I have some other pictures here's
some pictures of my kid playing soccer
I'll hit the right button and press it
once and it sets it to one star so if I
think that's a fourstar picture I can
rate it as four stars then when I import
it into Lightroom or my other photo
editing software it'll come up as being
four stars that way when you're in the
field and you find a picture that you
like and you want to remember you can
set it to four or five stars and when
you import them you'll be able to
quickly find that picture I just it's a
simple thing but I find it really really
really useful if you're viewing pictures
and you decide you want to delete a
picture of course there's a trash can
here you can press the trash can and
then touch eras or scroll over with a
scroll wheel there is an option for
changing erase to be the default so you
don't have to scroll over every time and
I find that really speeds things up so
I'll show you how to do that now hit the
menu
button scroll over to the custom camera
settings option here
and then on page four scroll down to
default erase option select that and set
it to erase selected so with that set
when I review a picture and I hit the
erase button Now erase is set by default
so if you need to go through and delete
10 pictures you can just quickly hit
play set play set play set play set and
that will erase those pictures in
sequence it just makes things much
faster and easier your live view this
camera has great live view capabilities
you can start live view at any time by
hitting the start stop button here what
this does is it flips up the viewfinder
the the mirror in the view that sends
there's a mirror in here that sends
light up here to your viewfinders and
that's what you see when you hold it up
to your eye it flips that out of the way
so that the sensor is getting a live
feed of the video of of the world around
you and it shows it on the back screen
here live view is good on this camera
because the live view focusing is really
good so I can just touch the screen here
and it should focus it for me well it
wants me to push F on oh I see it's
okay so you can touch to focus the
screen you can also push afon to focus
just like when you're reviewing a
picture you can press the info button
multiple times to view different bits of
information so if I am in my view I
really like to have the histogram on
because that tells me more about the
exposure so by looking at the histogram
here I can see well nothing's in the
right quarter of the histogram so I know
it's a little underexposed and I can
just crank up the exposure comp ation
here and see the changes in real time to
both the preview and to the histogram
live view is really terribly useful I
will warn you though because there's no
articulating screen if you get download
to the ground or over your head it can
be a little bit hard to see um one way
to work around that is to hook up your
phone's Wi-Fi app so you can get a
stream of real time data to your phone
I'll show you how to use the Wi-Fi app
in just a little bit as I demonstrated
earlier this camera has a touchreen
screen and it's kind of the first for
the 5D series which is why I wanted to
mention it you can interact with menus
and of course touch the focus I'll show
you the Q menu here you see the Q button
it takes you to a lot of just really
useful kind of quick settings that you
might frequently change so you can get
to these through other shortcut buttons
too but it's it's handy to remember that
Q button is there especially if you're
unfamiliar with the camera like if I
want to change from one shot focusing to
Servo I can do that by just pressing the
Q button and uh making those changes I
could also quickly change to change you
know my jpeg settings for the different
memory
cards there you go just switch to Raw
all by using the touchcreen
um if you're an experienced photographer
you might not be accustomed to using the
test string but I strongly encourage you
to give it a shot like try it out and
get used to it in particular it's really
useful review for reviewing pictures CU
I might need to make sure that I got
this sharp picture and with the older
5DS you had to hit the little magnify
button over here and then Zoom way in
and this is just so much faster to zoom
right in and pan around and then I can
just switch to a previous picture and
pan around and make sure that I got the
shot trust me once you get to use the
once you become in the habit of using
the touch screen you're going to really
appreciate it I want to talk a bit about
Canon's ITR feature ITR is intelligent
tracking and recognition this is a
feature that I think is new to the 5D
series but it's been in like the 7D Mark
I and the Canon 1dx Mark I and 1dx
original it will spot a subject that you
focus on and then follow it as it moves
across the frame so if a subject moves
from the right side of the frame to the
left side of the frame it can track it I
want to make a couple of points about it
it's turned on by default and it's
configured to find Faces by default so
you don't need to turn it on and I I
suggest leaving it on the default
however we'll talk about focusing groups
in a little bit it only works when you
have have uh the group AF
or uh full all auto all autofocus points
turned on so you cannot use ITR with a
single autofocus point or with a a small
group of autofocus points only with the
larger groups of autofocus points and to
me that kind of limits the usefulness of
it I just wanted to save you the time of
trying to figure out how that feature
actually works something that causes a
lot of problems for people is the
diopter the diopter is like an ability
to dial in a glasses prescription into
your viewfinder so if your glass is wear
you can take your glasses off and hold
this up and see everything sharp I'm
wearing contacts right now but when I
don't have my contacts in I really like
to use it the diopter is located here
just to on the on the right side of the
viewfinder so what you want to do is
hold the camera up to your eye make sure
you have live view turned off and look
at the numbers at the bottom don't look
through the viewfinder CU things might
be out of focus but rather look at the
the numbers like like the iso number and
turn that diopter until everything is
nice and
sharp if you change the diopter and you
hand the camera to somebody else
everything's going to be blurry if you
pick up your camera and it seems like
the camera won't focus or everything is
blurry check the diopter it sometimes
get gets hit accidentally but a lot of
people think their camera's broken like
they can't get anything to focus anymore
and it's really just a little twist of
the diopter let's talk about aperture
priority now because this is a prograde
camera I'm going to assume that you know
the basics of when you should use
aperture shutter priority manual mode
Etc but maybe you're coming from Nikon
where the mode buttons work a little bit
different the 5D Series has a mode dial
over here and you can see TV here stands
for shutter priority I'm going to push
this center button in and then twist
that over to AV which is Aperture value
it's aperture priority you can see when
you don't have this button pushed in you
can't twist it so when you do want to
twist it you have to push it in and
twist it like that this button used to
get hit all the time in the original 5D
so it was a real godsend when they added
in that extra button if you don't know
what I'm talking about when I'm talking
about f-stops and aperture visit this
URL sdp.io fstop and I'll walk you
through the whole process or check out
chapter 4 in my book stunning digital
photography quickly aperture priority
gives you direct control over the f-stop
allowing you to use a small f-stop
number which equates to a large opening
of the lens or high f- stop number which
may gives you a little small opening on
the lens once you have the mode dial set
to AV you will use the main dial here to
change the aperture so if we look at the
LCD screen on top here we can see now
it's set to f2.8 you know what I will
turn on I'll hit info here to show the
information on the back of the screen
because it's easier to
see so now it's set to F28 here I can
turn the dial to the right and use a
higher f-stop number or to the left to
use a smaller f-stop
number you can't touch the info screen
for some reason so you still have to use
the main dial there this is a
demonstration of how it might impact
your pictures white open with a small
f-stop number you can see Chelsea there
on the left the background is extremely
blurred as we use higher f-stop numbers
the background starts to become clear
providing more context to the image but
perhaps adding more distracting elements
in as well talk about shutter priority
as I mentioned earlier it's indicated by
TV on the mode dial here rather than S
as in every other camera system once you
switch to TV the main di here changes
personalities whereas before this
changed the aperture now it changes the
shutter speed that's different from
other camera systems so you can see by
scrolling to the right I can go all the
way up to 1 18,000 of a second or I can
scroll to the left to go down and down
down and one quote mark means one full
second six quote marks means 6 seconds
and it will go all the way up to 30
seconds kind of an arbitrary limit
limit if you want to know more about
shutter speed and shutter priority visit
this URL sdp.io
settings but to quickly demonstrate the
reason you might want to control it is
to either show or freeze Motion in your
picture three pictures of my daughter
here on the left you can see at 1/8 of a
second she's on one of these spinning
marry go rounds at 1/8 the background's
very blurry at 130 if the background is
showing some detail but there's still
some blur and then when I switch to 11
12 fifth we're still moving but the
background is completely Frozen that's
the kind of situation where you want to
pull out shutter priority like sports
and action and that kind of thing manual
mode gives you control over both your
shutter speed and your aperture
simultaneously to select manual mode
push in the center button on the mode D
here and switch over to M now the main D
here gives you control over your shutter
speed just like it did in shutter
priority to control your aperture you'll
use a secondary dial here on the back
back and those are the important
settings now you might notice that you
now can't change your exposure
compensation exposure compensation does
matter because you have auto
ISO um what you can do is to switch back
into say aperture priority mode and then
move the secondary dial so here you can
see I'm adding in exposure compensation
I'm at plus two stops if I go back to
manual mode now it will retain that
increased exposure compensation so if
you are using auto ISO in manual mode
and you want exposure compensation
switch over to shutter priority or
aperture priority use a secondary dial
to dial that exposure compensation in
and then switch back to manual mode
that's different from some earlier Canon
cameras I'm going to give you a couple
of links here in case you want to dive
deeper into a specific topic of
Photography if you want to know more
about night photography visit this link
sdp.io
and P if you want to know more about
landscape photography visit sdp.io
LS if you want to know more about
Wildlife visit sdp.io
WL covered that
already for more information about
manual mode visit sdp.io slgo manual
bulb mode allows you to use shutter
speeds longer than 30 seconds to use
bulb mode set the mode dial here from M
over to b b is bulb mode and now what it
will do is it will keep the shutter open
for as long as you hold your finger on
the shutter button here that seems weird
you wouldn't want to do a one minute
exposure by holding your finger like
this for one minute right chances are
good you check the camera and you'd
probably get bored so in those cases the
most likely thing that you'll do is to
pull off this cover here and hook up
your remote shutter timer Canon makes a
remote shutter timer but it's way
overpriced uh the shutter timer I
usually use I would just just go to
Amazon and search for Canon 5D remote
shutter timer and pick up one of the
ones that's under 20 bucks there's not a
particular name for them because there's
a Chinese manufacturer that makes them
but they resell them under a bunch of
different brands so typically they're
under 20 bucks and that's what I've used
for more than a decade they work just
fine you can pick up a shutter timer
that works for earlier 5DS like the 5D
Mark I or the original 5D and it should
work just fine I'm going to take one
minute and just plug my books I have a
bunch of books stunning digital
photography is perfect if you're trying
to learn the Art and Science of
Photography I'm telling you how to use
the buttons on your camera but that
doesn't teach you about the important
aspects of Photography like mood and
expression and lighting and storytelling
I cover all that in photography and dig
deep into specific topics like portraits
and weddings and Wildlife and Landscapes
even things like HDR and underwater
photography macro photography I cover
all that here and it comes free with 14
hours of video training so if you're not
into books you can just watch the 14
hours of video it's the ebook is 10
bucks so that's incredibly cheap for
that much video training not to mention
the actual book Lightroom is the way
that I do most of my postprocessing and
organize my pictures you're probably
already using Lightroom if you have a 5D
if you want to learn how to actually get
the most out of Lightroom check out my
Lightroom book like this book it comes
with 14 hours of video that's a ton of
video training goes well to complement
the book itself Photoshop for the heavy
lifting when you really need to make a
picture perfect in post I have a book on
Photoshop now and like the other books
it's a full book but it also comes with
10 hours of video training and it's an
awesome price and if you have questions
about which lens tripod Studio lighting
or just about any other type of gear to
get check out my photography buying Guy
this is the big boy it's really big fat
book you can get them all at Amazon or
just about any other bookstore or you
can order them direct from us we ship
worldwide at sdp.io store the ebooks
start at 10 bucks and the paperbacks are
just a little bit more let's talk about
the different shutter modes by default
the camera will come in single shutter
mode and that means when you push the
button let's switch over to program mode
here it's just going to take one picture
to set it to continuous mode hit the
drive button up here the second button
and then click a uh click the secondary
dial here until you'll see looks like a
stack of copies and then an H
that turns you into continuous
mode and now as long as you hold the
shutter down it will keep firing up
until the point when it fills its buffer
so you can see it stopped firing there
that's because it it filled its buffer
if you get frustrated because it fills
its buffer too quickly there are a
couple of things you can do for one you
could just switch from raw to jpeg JPEG
files are smaller they store faster
therefore you won't run out of buffer as
quickly the other option is to get
faster cards if you're riding to both
memory cards it's going to buffer even
faster than normal so you could write to
one card as well though again you take
that risk that that card will fail get
both get fast cards for both slots and
that will increase the number of shots
you can get consecutively before it
starts to buffer there are some other
shutter modes and I'll use the the back
screen here U when I push the drive
button and then use the secondary dial
here you can see there's continuous high
and continuous low continuous low sounds
like this
because sometimes seven frames a second
The Continuous High speeded is a little
bit too fast you don't want to
necessarily take all that many pictures
you can also do silent single shooting
and that's a misnomer because it's not
actually silent but is
quieter so that's perfect if you're
shooting a wedding and it's at that
quiet part of the ceremony and you don't
want to disturb people or if you're a
photojournalist and you're shooting some
sort of scene where you want to be as
discreet as possible things like street
photography silent shooting is perfect
for that there's also a silent
continuous shooting mode which keeps
shooting as long as you hold the your
finger on the shutter and two self
timers one 10-second self timer and one
two second self timer the 10-second self
timer is for those times when you put
the camera on a tripod and then you go
run around behind your family and put
your arm around them and everybody
Smiles uh the 2cond self-timer is good
for when you have the camera on a tripod
you have live view to lock the mirror
open and you want to get the sharpest
picture possible possible because it
will the 2cond delay will eliminate any
shake you introduce to the camera by
pressing the shutter button uh rather
than do the uh 10-second timer I'm going
to show you how to use the Interval
Timer in just a second but first let's
talk about focusing modes that was the
shutter modes now we'll do the focusing
modes it's on the same button however
you can see it says Drive AF so I'll
push that same button here and now I can
switch use the main D to switch between
three different modes one shot AI Focus
I touched it I always forget it has a
touch screen one shot AI focus and AI
Servo one shot seeks focus and then
freezes as soon as it finds Focus AI
Servo continues to seek out uh sharp
focus on a subject even though it's
moving now on low-end cameras like the
T6 or T5 I would use one shot for almost
anything on this camera this has a
fantastic focusing system it's amazing
therefore I use continuous focusing all
the time because the fact is as long as
you're handholding the camera there's
always a little bit of movement your
body can move forward or back a little
bit and if using fast lenses with
shallow depth of field you will find
some shots are out of focus just because
your body shifted forward to back or
maybe your portrait subject shifted
forward to back I just find that I get a
higher hit rate when I'm using AI Servo
therefore I just use that all the time
for more information about focusing
modes visit sdp.io
Focus now let's talk about focusing
areas because the camera can be
configured to focus on a very small
point or to focus anywhere across a big
frame and for most Pro photographers
you're actually going to want to tell
the camera where to focus beginning
cameras they're beginners are don't
don't want to deal with it so they're
happy to let the camera just kind of
pick a focus point but for me I always
want to tell the camera where to focus
so the way you'll do that is is by using
this button here this kind of
nondescript button that has like
crosshairs in it so as I push that we
look at the back display again you can
see now it's showing me all the
different focusing options that I have
so push that
and all right and um this is weird
there's another button here next to the
main dial labeled M FN
so push your focus
area selector and then push mfn multiple
times to iterate through the different
options this is what I use almost all
the time which is spot AF spot AF is a
very precise focusing point it focuses
on a very small area and it's almost
always what I want especially with
things like portraiture it's critical
that you focus right on the eye and not
on the forehead or the eyebrow or even
the eyelashes therefore you want the
smallest focusing Point possible and
focusing is very very precise and very
fast in that mode so that's pretty much
what I use however you can also select a
bigger focusing point or a expanded area
AF where you can focus on something and
then it will kind of uh Focus well it
focuses on a broader area and you know
some valid reasons to use some of these
expanded area AF or a full Zone AF where
you can use ITR some of the valid
reasons for that are if you're following
a moving subject like a flying bird
against a blue sky it can be difficult
to put a small focusing point on a
moving subject like that it's much
easier if you tell the camera Focus
anywhere in this area that way if your
long telephoto lens moves just a hair
the camera won't lose focus it'll it'll
lock on that subject so for me I almost
always use that spot AF but then when
I'm actually tracking moving subject
I'll expand it and make my life just a
little bit
easier to move the focusing point I kind
of demonstrated this already but you can
just use this thumb stick here and it's
a great thumb stick they inherited it
from The 1dx Mark I and it's better than
was in the other
5DS you can see the same kind of
information mirrored when you have your
eye up to the
viewfinder this camera gives you a lot
of control over the focusing Behavior
you can tune it by hitting the menu
button and then scrolling over to the AF
menus over here and the Very first page
here you'll see by default they provide
three different cases case one is the
default versatile multi-purpose setting
case two continues to track subjects but
ignores possible
obstacles that can be useful if you're
shooting a football game or a soccer
game and you focus and you're tracking
somebody but then a defensive player
runs in front of them it will ignore
this sudden obstruction rather than
quickly focusing on it it requires a bit
of intelligence right cuz it could just
decide to focus on whatever appears in
front of you and end up screwing up your
shot so that's good when you want it to
ignore things case three here instantly
focuses on subject suddenly entering the
area AF and that's good for times when
you want it to
focus no matter what you want it to
focus where your focusing point is no
matter what without any delay now if one
of those cases doesn't exactly meet your
needs you can go through go scroll down
even lower and specific configure the
tracking sensitivity the acceleration
and deceleration tracking and the AF
Point Auto switching the AF Point Auto
switching as it as it tracks a subject
across the frame from say the left side
of the frame to the right side of the
frame so with all that said I shoot a
lot of sports and Wildlife a lot of
action and I've never found that it
helps to change those settings I have
spent lots of time t a lot a lot of time
tuning them but whenever I tune them I
always end up a little frustrated with
it and I end up switching back to the
default so I wanted to tell you where it
is but I also encourage you just like
not to sweat it give the default
settings a try and only if you feel like
the AF system isn't behaving up to your
expectations should you go in and tune
it because it's it's probably going to
be fine let's talk about talk about how
to change the iso and the the iso is the
camera's sensitivity to light basically
if you're in a dim condition you would
use a high ISO like ISO 6400 if you're
in bright sunlight you'd probably use
ISO 100 if you want more information
about ISO including why I'm saying ISO
and not spelling out ISO visit this URL
sdp.io ISO to set the iso in this camera
there's a button on the top so I'll just
hit that ISO button there and then I can
use the main dial to select the
iso that's all there is to it if I
scroll all the way to the left it will
use auto ISO there is no shame in using
auto ISO I use some form of Auto
exposure almost all the time I will
often be in manual mode specifying both
my shutter speed and my aperture but
relying on the camera to determine the
exposure using auto ISO camera's Auto
exposure system is really fast and
really intelligent I just find I have a
higher hit rate when I use auto
ISO let's talk about exposure
compensation I mentioned it earlier you
can use exposure compensation in either
aperture priority or shutter priority
mode by simply moving the secondary dial
here down low and the picture will
become darker up high and the picture
will become brighter for more
information about exposure compensation
visit sdp.io
closely related to exposure compensation
is bracketing so to turn on bracketing
you actually have to go into the menu
system that's different from some other
cameras but I'll hit menu here and let's
go over to the camera icon page two Expo
compae Canon's menu naming is isn't
always Crystal Clear I'll hit the set
button and now what you see is a kind of
an exposure compensation diagram and if
I move the main Dow here it will split
off
and show this lower line here and what
it's saying now is it's going to take
three pictures at three different
exposures one at negative -2 stops one
at what it thinks the proper exposure is
and then one at two stops
Overexposed now if I want the whole
thing to be more exposed I can use the
exposure compensation dial anyway the
the visual there is really really useful
once you set it don't just hit the
shutter button or it will forget all
your settings hit the set button here
it's if you forget to hit set I do it
all the time it forgets it but I'll take
three pictures
now and as I review those three pictures
you can
see properly exposed underexposed and
Overexposed when you're done with
exposure compensation you'll have to go
back in in and turn it off
manually three stops exposure
compensation is usually enough
especially when I'm shooting raw because
this camera has a great dynamic range
you can also bracket at five stops of
exposure compensation so hit the menu
button and then under the custom
settings icon up here page one you'll
see bracketing number of bracketed shots
so if you select that you can choose
three shots Two Shots five shots or
seven shots often just to be safe I'll
bracket at actual at five stops and get
even more pictures taken you can also
turn on bracketing Auto cancel in case
you always want to automatically cancel
bracketing after your first time anytime
I do turn on bracketing I tend to take
three or four different scenes bracketed
so I don't use the bracketing Auto canel
normally but maybe you do and I wanted
you to know where it
is let's talk about Wi-Fi on this camera
this camera supports Wi-Fi that will
allow you to transfer pictures from the
camera over to your smartphone so that
you can share them online a little more
quickly it's not the best most people I
think try out the Wi-Fi app and then
probably never use it again or maybe you
use it once or twice you don't use it on
a regular basis it's kind of laborious
and as you'll see the smartphone app is
not up to par with other smartphone apps
that you might have on your phone uh but
I will show you how to use it so hit the
menu button here and it's it's really
poorly named turning on Wi-Fi is not
easy but you'll see under the wrench
icon page four communication settings
you'd think Canon might call it Wi-Fi or
something they call it communication
settings so we'll select built-in
wireless settings WiFi NFC and then
enable and now we have Wi-Fi enabled uh
we can also scroll down a couple and if
I select this option well I had to
connect to the smartphone first okay so
now I have my smartphone out this camera
does support NFC so if you have an
Android phone that supports NFC you
should be able to just rub it okay it
connected
in if you have an iPhone or NFC is not
working for you you will have to open up
your Wi-Fi
settings the way it works is the camera
creates a wireless access point usually
named 5D 4 and and oh Wi-Fi got turned
off somehow now you'll need to turn on
Wi-Fi on your camera under communication
settings built-in wireless settings go
to Wi-Fi function select connect to
smartphone and then
connect connect to device okay it's a
lot of unnecessary steps now the little
blinky thing up here will show Wi-Fi is
on the camera is now acting as a
wireless access point without internet
access but nonetheless a wireless access
point so if you have NFC on your phone
you can tap it here and it should
automatically connect in otherwise if
you don't have an SC like if you have an
iPhone you have to open up your wireless
wi-fi settings and connect to the
smartphone Network so here you can see
it's called EOS 54 and then some random
numbers that it assigned so I'll select
that and I'll click
connect this disconnection from your
internet even if you're using a Cellular
Connection you usually can't get to the
internet at this point so you have to
transfer the pictures over now that I'm
connected I can switch back to the Canon
Connect app presumably you've installed
this from your app store and remote
shooting allows me to see through the
camera that's mostly useful if the
camera is far away from you if you put
on a tripod and you want to be able to
compose the shot you can touch the
refocus here
take pictures and do things like um
change the shutter speed Etc overall it
gets the job done for remote shooting
for me usually what I'm doing is I'm
transferring pictures from the camera to
my phone so I can share them on
Instagram or Twitter press images on
camera there and what it will do is
browse through all the latest pictures
um some of them you'll see are labeled
raw and you can still transfer those
fortunately so you can s select
that and then tap this down here the
little phone with an arrow icon tap that
and it will transfer it to your phone
now this is it's weird because there's
no share button so you want to put this
on Twitter or something you'll have to
actually open up the app
separately
and browse for it and then you'll find
it alongside your regular smartphone
pictures generally you want to keep
Wi-Fi off and like I said it's a little
bit of a clumsy thing another option if
you find that frustrating is you can get
memory card readers like SD or CF memory
card readers that Connect into your
smartphone Android or iOS and then you
can use Lightroom mobile to import them
from the memory card sometimes that's
easier than fussing with
Wi-Fi now let's talk about raw I almost
always shoot raw images raw images
capture all the data from the camera
sensor including details like details
captured in highlights or Shadows that
are lost when you say when the camera
saves the files as a JPEG jpeg is the
default however so I recommend everybody
go in and turn on
raw and to do that you'll go to the very
first page here it's so important they
make it the very first thing select that
and now by using either the main dial or
the secondary dial here you can record
choose whether it records raw JP Peg or
both raw and jpeg generally I just used
raw and no jpeg for detailed information
about why you might want to use raw
visit
sc. raw V jpeg this camera also features
dual pixel raw a first Ry can and Camera
you could turn it on from the same menu
camera icon page one the second item
down here selecting enable here I will
warn you though I find absolutely no
value in using dual pixel raw we tested
it thoroughly
we could not create a real world
scenario where it actually helped the
situation and enabling dual pixel raw
includes several negative side effects
including your maximum frame rate drops
from 7 frames a second to 5 frames a
second it also doubles the size of your
files meaning they take up twice as much
storage they take longer to write they
take longer to import and processing
them will be slower
two uh another downside to using dual
pixel raw is the only way to make dual
pixel raw change ches is to use the
Canon software the Canon digital
photography professional software on
your PC or Mac and unanimously everybody
hates that
software I am not going to go into more
detail about dual pixel raw we do have a
review and examples on our Channel if
you want to search for that otherwise I
will just say go ahead and turn it off
and just leave it
off this camera includes several
different metering modes and I always
leave it in the default metering mode
because I'm always very happy with that
if you want to use a different metering
mode metering is the camera's Logic for
determining how bright or dark the
picture should be there's this button
here the first button you can see the
symbol for metering is universally this
weird circle with a dot in it so push
that and now I can use the main dial to
switch between evaluated metering which
is the default and very logical um
partial metting metering spot metering
or Center weighted average these are
kind of holdovers from the film era
that's the way I feel about it if you
are an old film shooter and you know how
to use spot metering and you're more
comfortable with that by all means use
it for everybody else I recommend just
using evaluated metering and then
adjusting with exposure compensation as
needed 5D markv does not include a
built-in flash however you can connect
an external flash and if you do you
might want to know how to change the
flash exposure compensation to make it
brighter or darker it's the third button
here so I'll push that button and now by
using the second dial I can add flash
exposure compensation the symbol is
lightning bolt plus or minus that's
Universal so I can dial that up or I can
dial it down to Output less flash for me
I like TTL but I find it almost always
puts out too much Flash and it blinds
people and washes out their faces I'd
rather use more ambient light so as a
result I tend
to dial in about negative one and a
third stops of flash exposure
compensation and just kind of leave it
there you can change the white balance
settings on this camera and that won't
make any real difference if you're
shooting raw but if you're shooting jpeg
you might want to get it right I find
the auto wi balance just generally works
the best anytime I try to fuss with it I
end up forgetting it and screwing up a
bunch of shots so it's something I never
really change but if you do want to
change it it's the first button here
you'll see WB so you push that and then
the secondary dial here will allow you
to browse through all the different
white balance options don't know what
I'm talking about when I say white
balance you probably shouldn't sweat it
but if you do want to understand go to
chapter three in my book stunning
digital photography because I Do cover
it in there let's talk about video
capabilities on this camera to record
video you'll take this dial here and
switch it over to the video camera
you'll see live view will automatically
pop up you can iterate through different
amounts of information on the screen by
hitting the info button
here this camera features both HD and 4K
video If you record in HD which is like
1080p um it can go up to 60 frames a
second and it will record the full width
of the frame if you record in 4K video
which is kind of everybody's favorite it
has about a 1.7x crop but it's also
going into um that's like a true 4K
which is a little bit wider than the
type of 4K that you're watching when you
watch this video on YouTube it's 4096
pixels wide as opposed to 3840 pixels
wide so just I'm mentioning that because
if you are shooting 4K and your
destination format is 3840 you will have
to keep in mind that you have to crop
off a bit of this off the sides so don't
compose too tight leave yourself a
little bit of room for cropping to
change your video format hit the menu
button
here
and go over
to camera icon page four scroll down to
movie recording quality and select
that now movie recording size select
that you can see by default it's set to
fhd which is full HD that's
1080p if you want 4K you'll scroll up to
4K and then either 23.98 frames a second
24 frames a second basically or 2997
which is basically 30 frames a second 24
frames a second is more typical for film
and 30 frames a second is more typical
for video and TV so I'll select
that
and so now when I turn it on now I just
want to show you the amount of crop that
you get here this is live view for a
still photo you can see the size of that
video slide as I switch to video it
crops in substantially so that's
something you really need to be aware of
if you are switching from Stills to
video on a regular basis there's a
significant crop factor it gets much
much tighter as a result a zoom lens is
useful so you can always Zoom back you
might also have to plan different lenses
and the lens I like to use for
video is the Canon 16 to35 F4 it's great
for video because it's super wide the 16
here basically becomes about 24 mm so
it's much more zoomed in than you might
expect this lens also has image
stabilization which can really help out
in handheld
situations and that's about what you
should know for video of course the
onboard mic isn't that great so you want
to uh connect in an external microphone
I'll have a suggestion for you and
you'll want to use headphones just to
make sure there's no problems with your
external microphone as I mentioned
earlier the file sizes are massive
they're absolutely massive so not only
do you want a bigger memory card to
record those huge files but when you do
import them onto your computer the first
thing you want to do is probably
transcode it down to a smaller file size
and then if you don't have the extra
storage actually get rid of the original
files we use vidcoder to transcode these
massive motion JPEG files down to a more
reasonable uh codec and that kind of
makes life much easier this camera also
includes GPS the global positioning
system which can find your place
anywhere on the planet and then tag your
pictures with it and this is awesome
because when you tag your pictures with
GPS you can import them in Lightroom and
then go to the map Tab and see the
location of all the different pictures
that you've taken it means that if you
think oh I need to find that picture
that I took in Boston you can pull up
the map and then zoom in our map and
actually find the exact street that you
were on it makes it easier to find
pictures and it's also just kind of cool
if you're a landscape photographer and
you want to revisit a location even if
you were on a hike or something you can
actually pull that information out and
find your way back to that spot I've
also found that GPS does not use that
much battery uh I kept it on for an
entire week of traveling and didn't have
any problems to turn on GPS so basically
I just turn on GPS and I just leave it
so I'll hit the menu button here and
then I need to go over to this wrench
icon and it's on page four right above
communication settings is GPS settings
so I'll select that select
GPS and I'll turn it on to mode two mode
one keeps the GPS on all the time even
when the camera is turned off so it's
going to burn through a lot more
batteries Mo 2 is a little more sensible
it only picks GPS signals when the
camera is on but that means that there
might be a little bit of lag it might
not immediately get a GPS signal the
first time you turn it on so I have it
on mode two and you can see there are
some other options here like the
position update interval um 15 seconds
is generally okay with me um to save
some batteries I will even lengthen it
because usually not moving that fast
when I'm taking pictures and every 1
minute might reduce the battery usage by
four Factor um but still be good enough
for me me and you can also turn on a GPS
logger if you absolutely want to this
doesn't change the fact that whether you
not you have the GPS logger on it's
going to be saving your GPS data to your
pictures the GPS logger just literally
saves a log of your GPS location and you
could open that up later and actually
see the path where you walked even if
you weren't taking pictures I if you
actually want that I would instead
suggest that you get a smartphone app
and run it from your smartphone so that
you're not killing your your cameras
batteries and smartphone apps will
actually show it on the map and be a
little more useful for you now I'll show
you the Interval Timer the Interval
Timer will take pictures on a regular
basis and that's terribly useful for
doing time lapses uh or if you're
stitching together a long exposure by
using a technique like image averaging
the Interval Timer is just perfect I
also prefer the interval timer for
situations where uh I need to be in the
photo where I need to set the camera up
and on a tripod and then run around
behind my family I'll set the Interval
Timer to take 10 pictures that way you
don't have to keep running back and
hitting the shutter button again and
again so to activate the Interval Timer
hit the menu
button and it's over on the camera
icon page four Interval Timer select
that it's set to disable by default so
I'll select enable and this is
confusing um don't hit your shutter
button or it will forget your settings
instead you'll need to hit set but
before you do that you'll need to hit
the info button you can see it says info
detail set hit the info button here and
select the interval so for me if I'm
taking a selfportrait I'm us usually
have it fire off one shot every 5
seconds and I'll set the number of shots
to say take 20
shots and then I'll scroll down to okay
so now I've set those options
and whether or not you set the options
when you select enable you need to be
sure to hit set hit set when you're done
because if you hit the shutter the
Interval Timer will not be enabled now
when I hit the shutter button it will
fire the first shot right away and then
wait 5 seconds and fire the next shot
again up until it takes the number of
shots that I told it to if I want to cut
it off early I'll just turn the camera
off mirror lock up is a technique a lot
of us used in in the earlier days to
reduce the amount of vibration every
time you take a picture with an SLR
using the viewfinder The Mirror Has to
flip up and that can shake the camera a
little bit reducing your sharpness
especially on high megapixel bodies like
this the new technique that I prefer is
just use live view so just hit that
start stop button there turn the camera
on first hit the start stop
button this flips the mirror up
eliminating that and it gives you the
ability to more precisely focus and
frame your shot by giving you a live
feed through res just use that instead
of mirror lock up there's still the
option for Mirror lock up but I can't
imagine a reason to use it anymore when
you filled up your memory cards you will
want to format them so you can reuse
them of course when you filled up your
memory cards and then transfer them over
someplace safe like your computer with
an active backup to format your memory
cards this is something I do regularly
go to the wrench icon page one and then
the last option here is format card
you'll have to select which of the two
cards you want to format and then select
okay to actually format it now if you
accidentally format your card and you
did not mean to if there are still
pictures on there that you need here's a
useful tool photo W go to
scpo like Photo recover that's a free
tool for Windows Mac Linux just about
anything that will go through your
memory card and recover any files that
it happens to find because when you
format the card it's like ripping out
the table of contents from a book all
the pages are still there it's just you
have to go through one page at a time to
find it so it does that for you saves
all your pictures onto your computer and
it can be a lifesaver if you search for
image recovery software Google will give
you a bunch of options that cost like 50
bucks or more they pretty much all use
the same free tool so save your money
just use the free photo tool I've used
it a bunch of times it's great one thing
I hate about all cameras is they come
with a beep turned on by default I hate
that because I'm a wedding for
photographer and you know when the
church is quiet and Uncle John is
holding up his little little uh Canon
camera and it's beeping as it focuses
beep it's so annoying um though actually
this camera hasn't been beeping so maybe
it's not turned on by default but I'll
show you how to turn it off just in case
it is on camera page one and the menu
item go down to the fourth item down
here beep says enable set it to disable
because nobody wants to hear the beep
back button focus is one of my favorite
techniques back button Focus separates
focusing from the shutter button so by
default when you push the shutter button
halfway the camera will focus everybody
kind of expects that but experienced
people have many situations where you
want to take a picture but you do not
want the camera to automatically Focus
back button Focus links the afon button
here with the focusing Behavior and the
shutter button turns it off so when you
want to take a picture without focusing
you don't push the afon button when you
do want to focus you push the afon
button if you want more information
about why you should use back button
Focus visit this link sdp.io
ybb now I'll show you how to actually
configure it on this camera I'll hit the
menu button here and got to scroll all
the way right over to the custom
settings menu here it's this camera with
lines under it and scroll over to the
right some
more down to page three select the last
option here which is custom controls so
I'll select that and this allows you to
change the behavior of the buttons and
it's kind of limited on camera Canon
cameras but one of the useful things you
can do is enable back button Focus so
I'll select the shutter button here and
press set and by default you'll see it's
set to metering and AF start I'm going
to set it to just metering start so in
other words I'm turning off AF start
from the shutter button now I'll scroll
down to afon and make sure that's set to
metering and AF
start here's a bonus that you get with
the newer Canon cameras this little
asterisk button here which is normally
AE lock I never use that instead what
I'll do is I'll configure it to do a
different type of AF start so I'll
select that asterisk there and I'll
select metering and AF start just like I
did before but I'll hit the info button
you see it says info detail set so I'll
hit that and now I can select the exact
behavior of that AF start button when I
push that and what I'm going to do is I
almost always want AF AI Servo because
that's awesome so I'll set that and the
way I like to configure it is I set it
the afon and the asterisk for different
area selection modes so I'll select AF
area selection mode here and for the
asterisk I tend to use Auto selection AF
the widest range of focusing points that
will allow the camera to decide where to
focus so I'll set that and now I'll go
back and edit the afon button here I'll
hit the info to change the settings and
I'll set the afon button to do the spot
AF so
now when I want spot AF a tiny little
small precise focusing point I'll push
AF on when I want to focus anywhere I'll
push the asterisk here that's Chang the
way I do Wildlife photography especially
if there's a bird perched in a tree and
there's all sorts of twigs and leaves
that I need to avoid focusing on I'll
use the spot AF and put the AF point
right on the bird's eye if there's a
flying bird and I'm using a big
telephoto lens and it's kind of hard to
keep the spot AF on I'll just move my
thumb over a little bit and I'll hit the
asterisk instead allowing the camera to
find the bird anywhere in the frame the
fact that I don't have to go in and
change settings is incred incredibly
incredibly useful so thank you Canon for
building that in the menus are
incredibly confusing and also poorly
named one thing you can do to make it
much much easier is to set up your own
custom my menu my menu just has those
those menu settings that you use on a
regular basis and it's the last menu
item here the little as the little star
and the first thing you'll do is Select
add my menu tab so your menu will have
tabs and then each tab can have items so
we'll add a menu one tab here and then
we'll choose to configure it select
items to register and now you can see I
can go through a long list of every
single menu item here so if you find
yourself regularly changing the image
quality you might add that to my menu
and what else do we usually change we
will'll often format pictures oh I use
the Interval Timer all the time so I'll
turn on I'll add that
um in video mode I will often have to go
in and change the audio levels so I just
went past
that sound recording so I'll add that
and I'll hit menu to back up but now you
can see my menu here now has three
different menu items so I don't have to
dig through each of the different tabs
anymore I can just go right to my menu
here and pick the menu item it just
makes it so much
easier that covers my tutorial for the
Canon 5D markv now I'm going to go over
my favorite accessories for it both
software and Hardware up first Adobe
Lightroom Lightroom processes your
ingest all of your pictures so you
insert your memory card into the
computer and then it will pull in your
thousands of pictures render previews
for them and allow you to do basic
editing like changing the exposure
cropping rotating leveling even fixing
some blemishes and stuff such Lightroom
is kind of a necessity it's slow as heck
but I still think it's the best software
out there uh I suggest getting the
Lightroom CC deal the Creative Cloud
deal because that's the only way you get
new updates for it you can get it from
sdp.io Adobe deal with Photoshop and in
the US it's usually about 10 bucks a
month let's talk lenses for General
shooting my favorite lens is the Canon
24 to70 F28 this is one of the sharpest
zoom lenses ever made it's absolutely
exceptional uh it's also quite fast at
F28 making it good for events things
like wedding receptions where you're
shooting indoors in kind of low light
it's basically the best thing there is
unfortunately it's not image stabilized
there is no image stabilized version of
it in the Canon World um unless you go
for the Tamron version I still like the
Canon better um because it well there
has a few minor differences like it
doesn't have Focus breathing anyway the
Canon is my recommendation you can pick
it up from the link down here and we get
a few pennies out of every dollar that
you
spend for video as I mentioned earlier I
recommend the Canon 16 to35 F4 because I
shoot 4K video that means I get
basically a 1.8x crop which means I need
to be shooting with a super wide angle
lens to be a normal wide angle lens it's
also image stabilized which is really
important for any sort of Run and Gun
video shooting handheld or even on a
mopod that imem stabilization helps if
you're a landscape phot photographer and
you want to shoot Ultra wides the Canon
11 to 24 just can't be beat it's an F4
lens there's no image stabilization and
it's exceptionally pricey but it's super
sharp and it's an 11 mm Zoom it can
shoot as wide as you might ever need
basically you can get it from sdp.io
C11 if you're doing portraits this is an
unbeatable lens it's the Canon 24 or
Canon 70 to 200 F28 I have a telecon
converter on here now because I was
shooting sports with it it's very sharp
it has no Focus breathing and it's this
lens is the reason we stay in the Canon
system it's a spectacular spectacular
lens if you're shooting sports more than
portraits you could also consider the
Tamron 7200 F28 it's even sharper but it
shrinks significantly when you're
shooting close-up portraits this lens
does not have Focus breathing it's been
an important criteria for us we love
that lens um a couple of telecon
converters are terribly useful with the
7200 so if you pick that up you might
want to pick up the 1.4x or 2x
teleconverters it still continues to be
quite sharp because it's a really high
quality lens you can use these links
here the 1.4x telecon converter will
turn it into um like uh what is it 100
to 280 mm or so lens and the 2x
teleconverter will turn it into a 140 to
400 mm f56
lens if you're Shooting Sports and you
have some money to throw around check
check out the Canon 200 to 400 MM F4
lens it's expensive but it's fantastic
it's extremely sharp and fast and it has
a lot of reach it also has a built-in
1.4x telecon converter so you can get
out to like 560 mm and f56 which is
great it's also good even for wildlife
stuff if you just want an inexpensive
Wildlife lens this lens you can pick it
up for about a grand maybe a little bit
less I would even find a used version
cuz they're extremely durable
the Canon 400 MM f56 Prime this is an
old lens it's got to be 13 years old now
but we've been using it this whole time
and it cannot be beat at that price
point no image stabilization but for
things like moving Birds it works
spectacularly and you usually don't have
too much of a need for image
stabilization with high shutter speeds
anyway sc.
ic400 another good Wildlife lens that is
stabilized and a little more versatile
it's actually a hair sharper but way
more expensive
is the Canon 1400 mm Mark 2 Zoom do not
get the Mark 1 Zoom it had appalling
image quality we found this version to
be much much better pick it up at the
link here if you're serious about
Wildlife well first I would probably
push you towards a 7D Mark I because
you'll get even better images or maybe a
Canon 5dsr as the body but for lenses
you cannot beat the Canon 600 mm F4
you're looking at about 13 Grand for it
but it's spectacular it will produce
results that simply cannot be
beat if you're shooting video a good mic
is critical for interview style things
or anyone where you're filming somebody
talking our favorite lab mic is the
Sennheiser ew100 G3 that's what I'm
using now you can pick it up from this
link here you can also save yourself a
few bucks and pick up a G2
used if you want to order prints we have
a whole video that test tested all the
major printers in the United uned States
visit sdp.io print it to see that if
you're looking for a tripod I always
recommend this cheap $50 tripod from DOA
pick it up at this link here but I also
wanted to recommend a higher-end menoto
tripod one that we actually tend to use
on a regular basis which is oh it's
cleverly named right MK 190x Pro 4-
bhq2 those Italians in their clever
naming anyway you can use this link down
here to check it out but it's an
excellent functional tripod it's a
little bit bigger than a travel tripod
but generally bigger and heavier tripods
are better to use as long as you don't
have to carry it with you for many miles
the Canon flashes especially the 600
exrt they're excellent but they're also
very very expensive and kind of
unnecessarily so if you just want a
cheap on camera flash I'll recommend the
yongo YN 568 ex2 it pretty accurately
simulates the like non-radio controlled
Canon flashes at a much much lower price
point so play with this and see if it
gets the job done for you before you
start dropping five 600 bucks on Canon
flashes before my voice gives out one
last plug for my books stunning digital
photography teaches you all the
photographic things you need to know
beyond the buttons and dials on your
cameras I teach you the Art of
Photography posing mood expression the
things that really make a difference in
your photography and heck you spent 3400
bucks on a camera body you can spend 10
20 bucks on some knowledge right some Ed
tion if you're baffled by all the
different lens options flash options
Studio lighting how to build out a
studio uh anything gear related is
covered in my photography buying guide
with tons and tons of video in it my
Photoshop book when you get serious
about your post-processing you want to
make your pictures your portraits your
Landscapes perfect you will definitely
be using Photoshop this book is cheap
and has 10 hours of video and of course
for those processing your pictures in
Lightroom I have a book on that too pick
up any of those from our store atp.
store or just go to Amazon go to Amazon
and look at the reviews for the books
you don't have to take my word for it
other people will tell you their
experiences with the books the reviews
are good then you can get it directly
from us at sdp.io store that wraps it up
share with your friends subscribe to see
more photography videos we teach
photography and we review lots of gear
we look at your pictures live every
Thursday at 5:00 we'll actually give you
feedback if you tune in to the live show
share with your friends thanks and bye